Guide to the Richard T. LaPiere Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Richard T. LaPiere papers
1928-1961
SC0571
LaPiere, Richard T. (Richard Tracy), 1899-1986
2 Linear feet
These papers document LaPiere's writing career and include correspondence and reviews of THE FREUDIAN ETHIC and five of his other published books; typescript articles and lectures; typescripts of four unpublished books; and reprints of his scholarly articles.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Mrs. Richard LaPiere, 1999.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Richard T. LaPiere, a social psychologist, earned three degrees at Stanford University: his A.B. and M.A. in economics, 1926 and 1927 respectively, and his Ph.D. in sociology in 1930. He studied at the London School of Economics and Political Science (1927-28) before joining the Stanford faculty in 1929. He retired as professor emeritus of sociology in 1965. His published works include A THEORY OF SOCIAL CONTROL, THE FREUDIAN ETHIC, SOCIAL PSYCHOLOGY (with Paul R. Farnsworth), and WHEN THE LIVING STRIVE.
Description of the Collection
These papers document LaPiere's writing career and include correspondence and reviews of THE FREUDIAN ETHIC and five of his other published books; typescript articles and lectures; typescripts of four unpublished books; and reprints of his scholarly articles.
Access Terms
LaPiere, Richard T. (Richard Tracy), 1899-1986; America--Intellectual life--20th century.; Authors.; Manuscripts (for publication).
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Collective Behavior - correspondence and reviews, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Freudian Ethic - correspondence, 1958- Sept. 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Freudian Ethic - correspondence, Oct. 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Freudian Ethic - undated correspondence and misc. items (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Freudian Ethic - reviews, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Freudian Ethic - reviews, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Freudian Ethic - book catalogs (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Social Psychology - correspondence and advertisements, 1937-38 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Son of Han - correspondence and reviews, 1936-37 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Theory of Social Control - correspondence, 1954 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - When the Living Strive - correspondence, 1940-41 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - When the Living Strive - reviews, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Typescript article, "A Communistic China?" (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript article, "Global Opinion and the Maintenance of the Peace" (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Typescript article, "Global Utopianism" (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Typescript article, "Parable of the Perturbed Motor Car (A Brief Tour of the Social Sciences)" (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Typescript article, "Static Man in a Dynamic Age" (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Typescript article, "Word Magic; Man's Greatest Tool Turns Upon its Creator" (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Typescript lecture, [ethics of apathy] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Typescript lecture, "Marx and Freud: Ideologists of East and West" (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Typescript lecture, "Public Oponion" (Citizenship lecture 1934) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Typescript lecture, "Social Change and the Function of the School" Aug. 3, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Typescript chapters and notes on child psychology (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Typescript story, "The Patient Plumber" (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Typescript book: Chinese Red, Introduction and chapters 1-2 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Typescript book: Chinese Red, chapters 3-5 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Typescript book: Chinese Red, chapters 6-8 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Typescript book: Chinese Red, chapters 9-10 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Typescript book: Chinese Red, chapters 11-12 and bibliography (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Typescript book: Freedom of the Skies, chapters 1-4 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Typescript book: Freedom of the Skies, chapters 5-8 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Typescript book: Freedom of the Skies, chapters 9-end (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Typescript book: Freedom of the Skies, misc. items (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Typescript book: Living through Chaos, chapters 1-5 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Typescript book: Living through Chaos, chapters 6-10 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Typescript book: Living through Chaos, chapters 11-13 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Typescript book: Living through Chaos, chapters 14-16 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Typescript book: Winds of Freedom, chapters 1-3 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Typescript book: Winds of Freedom, chapters 4-7 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Typescript book: Winds of Freedom, chapters 8-10 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Typescript book: Winds of Freedom, chapters 11-13 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Typescript book: Winds of Freedom, chapters 14-end (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Meetings, programs from (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Published articles, speeches, etc. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Reprints, 1928-1935 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Reprints, 1936-1944 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Reprints, 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Signed copy of Son of Han (Harper & Brothers 1937) (Box 4, Folder 9)